<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE changes SYSTEM "./dtd/changes-v10.dtd">

<changes title="JAMES History of Changes">
  <devs>
    <person name="Federico Barbieri" email="scoobie@systemy.it" id="FB"/>
    <person name="Serge Knystautas" email="sergek@lokitech.com" id="SK"/>
    <person name="Charles Benett" email="charles@benett1.demon.co.uk" id="CB"/>
    <person name="Stuart Roebuck" email="stuart.roebuck@adolos.co.uk" id="SR"/>
    <person name="Ivan Seskar" email="iseskar@upsideweb.com" id="IS"/>
    <person name="Prasanna Uppaladadium" email="prasanna@vayusphere.com" id="PU"/>
    <person name="Gabriel Bucher" email="gabriel.bucher@razor.ch" id="GB"/>
    <person name="Danny Angus" email="danny@thought.co.uk" id="DA"/>
    <person name="Darrell DeBoer" email="?" id="DD"/>
    <person name="Harmeet Bedi" email="harmeet@kodemuse.com" id="HB"/>
    <person name="Matthew Pangaro" email="mattp@lokitech.com" id="MP"/>
    <person name="Jason Borden" email="jborden@javasense.com" id="JB"/>
    <person name="Samuel Sadek" email="Samuel.Sadek@kpmg.co.uk" id="SS"/>
    <person name="Stephan Schiessling" email="s@rapi.com" id="SS2"/>
    <person name="Eung-ju Park" email="colus@apache.org" id="EP"/>
    <person name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com" id="PH" />
    <person name="Jeff Keyser" email="JKeyser@telocity.com" id="JK" />
    <person name="Noel J. Bergman" email="noel@devtech.com" id="NjB" />
    <person name="Andrei Ivanov" email="myfam@surfeu.fi" id="AI" />
    <person name="Peter M. Goldstein" email="farsight@alum.mit.edu" id="PG" />
    <person name="Brad Walker" email="bwalker@studentadvantage.com" id="BW" />
    <person name="Christian Buchegger" email="christian.buchegger@planet-interkom.de" id="CB2" />
    <person name="Shilpa Dalmia" email="shilpa@postx.com" id="SD" />
    <person name="Steve Short" email="sshort@postx.com" id="SS3" />
  </devs>

<release version="2.1" date="Expected release December 2002">
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Fixed platform-specific performance issue with the POP3 server delivery.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="update">
    Fixed bug where RemoteDelivery did not iterate through all MX records on connect failure.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="update">
    Updated James to use the Avalon Framework version 4.1.3.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="update">
    Updated James to use Avalon Phoenix version 4.0.1.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="doc">
    Added extensive commenting - specifically Javadoced the vast majority of methods.
  </action>
  <action name="PG,AI" type="code">
    Added a James specific abstract Service implementation.  Unified configuration, logging, as well as enabling the use of thread pools and socket types on a per service basis.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Corrected JDBCMailRepository to obey stated contract.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,PG" type="code">
    Adjusted service handlers to flush socket output streams to ensure prompt client interactions.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Adjusted the NNTP server so that it better conforms to the NNTP specification (see bug #13564 for details).
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Corrected a typo that had been disabling NNTP using SSL functionality.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Corrected an architectural flaw in the NNTP server implemenation that disabled NNTP authentication.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Fixed a bug in the GenericListserv subject normalization.  Neatened the code to make later modifications easier.
  </action>
  <action name="BW" type="code">
    Fixed a bug in the RemoteDelivery mailet that caused the mailet to unnecessarily split the recipient list when using a gateway.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,PG" type="code">
    Added object pooling for service handlers to substantially improve performance.
  </action>
  <action name="AI,PG" type="code">
    Added a new Watchdog interface to effectively support connection timeouts.  An implementation of the interface was added that uses a second thread per connection to ensure timeouts.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,PG" type="code">
    Resolved a memory leak in the source - a list of files to be deleted was being maintained that was unnecessary.  The file to be deleted is now deleted immediately after it is no longer needed.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Changed the code to ensure that all thread pool threads are returned to the thread pool in a non-interrupted state.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Centralized the file/directory lookup code inside James and fixed it so that it handled absolute URLs properly.
  </action>
  <action name="AI,PG" type="code">
    Added a more substantial connection manager.  This connection manager allows us to limit the maximum number of client connections per server socket.  It also allows us to set the socket timeout for client sockets explicitly.
  </action>
  <action name="DA,PG" type="code">
    Added enabled/disabled switch to main server components.
  </action>
  <action name="DA" type="code">
    Added new FetchPOP functionality, to allow James to consolidate mail from a number of POP3 servers in a single server.
  </action>
  <action name="DA" type="doc">
    Added documentation to demonstrate how to configure James as a universal sendmail relay.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Made subject prefix bracketing in GenericListserv configurable.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Added the HasHeader matcher.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Added the JDBCVirtualUserTable mailet.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Enhanced the RemoteAddrInNetwork and RemoteAddrNotInNetwork to accept domain names.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="update">
    Fixed the log configuration so that AM and PM entries are properly distinguishable by default.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Added a configurable debug parameter to several mailets to allow a more granular control of debug logging.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Added the Habeas warrant mailet and matcher.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,PG" type="update">
    Changed the server configuration to default log at INFO level.  Adjusted logging statements so that they are log level appropriate.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Fixed a critical bug in the dbfile implementation.  Fixed repository implementation so that db repositories do not behave as dbfile repositories.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Fixed MimeMessageWrapper so that mail headers are properly updated when headers are set on the wrapper.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Added UNSETFORWARDING functionality to the RemoteManager.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Closed an open relay hole involving an empty Sender header.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Fixed Oracle specific bug that limited us to messages of 4K or less in the repository.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,PG,SS" type="code">
    Ensured that a number of database and I/O resources are properly closed under all conditions.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Changed default column sizes for JDBC repositories to be RFC compliant.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="code">
    Fixed exception handling in JdbcDataSource when getConnection() fails.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Fixed NotifySender/NotifyPostmaster to be more robust against ill-formed headers in the email being forwarded.
  </action>
  <action name="SD,SS3" type="code">
    Made a substantial performance enhancement to the LinearProcessor such that mail changes are not persisted to the store until necessary.  Also reduced synchronization scope.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Converted String concatenation to the use of StringBuffers throughout the code base.
  </action>
  <action name="PG" type="code">
    Fixed date formatting to be thread safe.
  </action>
  <action name="PH" type="code">
    Upgrade James to the Avalon 4.0/4.1 actual releases.
  </action>
  <action name="NjB" type="update">
    Fixed InSpammerBlacklist
  </action>
  <action name="NjB,SK" type="update">
    Fixed MailImpl.duplicate to include remote addr, remote host, and last updated fields.
  </action>
  <action name="CB2" type="update">
    Fixed NNTP server bug where the NEXT command was not being properly dispatched and handled.
  </action>
  <action name="SK" type="update">
    Cleaned up error handling in LocalDelivery.
  </action>
  <action name="SS2" type="code">
    Changed the default configuration so that log files are appending by default.
  </action>
  <action name="SS2" type="update">
    Reported the lack of in.close in MimeMessageSource.getSize(), which was causing stranded file handles, especially during large POP3 sessions.
  </action>
  <action name="AI" type="update">
    Matcher config implementation object now properly set with matcher name.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="2.0a3" date="20-April-2002">
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    FileRepository should no longer produce 0-byte files.  It checks that the source is different than the target, or confirm it is in memory before saving to disk.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Removed check that connection is not closed before returning it.  The pooler is already confirming the connection was open before putting it in the pool, so this was a big unnecessary performance drain.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Fixed the delay in the JDBC mail spool repository as it wasn't rechecking correctly after it emptied the spool.
  </action>
  <action dev="SS2" type="code">
    Added dot-stuffing in POP3 message delivery to fix problems with Netscape and other mail clients and to comply with RFC.
  </action>
  <action dev="JK" type="code">
    Fixed bounce method to use the Return-Path header if there is one.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Improved handling of delivery error messages when the remote server returns a specific 5XY complaint.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Better diagnosing of temporary vs. permanent delivery exceptions, most notably "Could not connect to host.." is a temporary exception.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Remote SMTP delivery now sets the remote hostname using the servername configuration setting (uses the first one).
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Have it cleanly (not print stack trace) if the remote manager handler has io/socket exceptions.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Support in "IsSenderInFakeDomain" to handle null senders properly (was producing a false positive in this case).
  </action>
  <action dev="PH" type="update">
    Added releaseConnection method to BaseConnectionHandler as per Paul H's bug report.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Reordered 250 SMTP responses to fix Mac client issue per Giles Chanot's bug report.
  </action>
</release>

<release version="2.0a2" date="1-Dec-2001">
  <action dev="*" type="update">
    Moved to Avalon snapshot of November 2001
  </action>
  <action dev="DA" type="update">
    Fixed POP3 message size bug that prevented retrieval
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Added Mordred database connection pooling.  It is the marriage of Town's db pooling code and Excalibur's configuration.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Changed MailImpl.getSize() to getMessageSize() and from int to long.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="docs">
    Small updates to documentation
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Added JDBCListserv, straight JDBC implementation of old TownListserv that extends GenericListserv
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Patched bug in GenericListserv for when subject was null
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Got mailets/matchers to load from something besides james.bar
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Added scheduler notification during SMTP DATA reception and POP3 RETR sending so the connection handler doesn't time out connection while data is being transfered.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Support &lt;gatewayPort&gt; setting on RemoteDelivery to send all messages to a non-port 25 SMTP server.  Only makes sense when &lt;gateway&gt; is also set.
  </action>
  <action dev="EP" type="update">
    Used getAsBooleanValue in various configuration methods to make code more readable.
  </action>
  <action dev="SS" type="update">
    Added support for Oracle database for mail and spool JDBC repositories.
  </action>
</release>

<release version="2.0a1" date="30-Sep-2001">
  <action dev="CB,*" type="update">
    Moved to Avalon snapshot of 9-25-2001.
  </action>
  <action dev="HB" type="code">
    Added NNTP service.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Greatly improved multi-threading support for repositories and SMTP reception.
  </action>
  <action dev="JB" type="code">
    SMTP AUTH support
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Support null senders, i.e., MAIL RCPT: &lt;&gt;.
  </action>
  <action dev="DD,SK" type="update">
    Converted Town mail and user repositories to straight JDBC ones, using Excalibur connection pooling and configurable SQL statements per DB.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Messages are no longer loaded until absolutely necessary.
  </action>
  <action dev="GB" type="update">
    Fixed exception being thrown on MailAddress parsing.
  </action>
  <action dev="CB" type="update">
    Rebuilt CVS tree after hack and moved src to src/java.
  </action>
  <action dev="DA" type="code">
    New extensible, flexible Redirect mailet that handles notifications and forwarding.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    JDBC Alias mailet.
  </action>
  <action type="docs">
    Added a whole bunch of related RFCs to the webdocs.
  </action>
  <action dev="DA" type="update">
    Add date to bounced emails.
  </action>
  <action dev="HB" type="update">
    Updated DNS library and started process to move it to Avalon service.
  </action>
  <action type="update">
    More checks to fix "stuck file" problem in Avalon mail repository.
  </action>
  <action dev="MP" type="code">
    Limit the size of a message on reception (rather than waiting until processors).
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Fixed dot-stuffing in SMTP reception/delivery.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Improved how Return-Path and Received headers are generated during SMTP reception.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    More efficient remote delivery code, better error messages, and gateway parameter to route all messages to a single target.
  </action>
  <action dev="DA" type="update">
    Fixed timezone bug in RFC822DateFormat
  </action>
  <action dev="MP" type="update">
    Patch to support username@[yyy.yyy.yyy.yyy] addresses
  </action>
  <action dev="GB" type="update">
    Patch to fix size calculation from headers
  </action>
</release>

<release version="1.2.1" date="13-Dec-2000">
  <action dev="SK,SR,CB" type="update">
    Fix for "stuck file" problem in Avalon mail repository.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="design">
    Made usernames case insensitive on MailAddress
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Complete rewrite of processor code to send through Mail object through matchers and mailets.  Design might be less efficient but easier to understand and more flexible for later improvements to API.  Also no longer "loses" IP address and error message information when Mail object go from one processor/state to the next (ToProcessor changed as well now that processor works).
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Updated to JavaMail 1.2.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Changed instantiation of recipients on a Mail object to a Set (HashSet) whenever possible in preparation for the API having this change.
  </action>
  <action dev="IS" type="code">
    Added UsersTownRepository to let you maintain user lists in a database
  </action>
  <action dev="SR" type="update">
    In POP3 handler, properly includes headers in calculating size of messages.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Removed "synchronized" attribute on many methods in town and file spool repositories.  Should significantly boost performance and multithreaded capabilities.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Optimization of town mail repository, introduction of JamesMimeMessageInputStream and the James MimeMessage.  Should significantly reduce the number of unnecessary parses or saves on MimeMessages in server.
  </action>
  <action dev="SR" type="update">
    Properly calculates hashCode for MailAddress so duplicates do not exist in Hashmaps
  </action>
  <action dev="SR" type="update">
    Hardcoded serialVerUID on MailAddress and MailImpl to that of James 1.2 release so future releases can continue to use mail stored in earlier releases.
  </action>
  <action dev="IS" type="update">
    Added ability on NotifySender and NotifyPostmaster to attach informative notice.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    GenericListservManager now requires existsAddress() which it uses to prevent someone already on the list from subscribing or someone not on the list from removing themselves.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Changed User repository for file to *always* end the destination with a File.separator.  Otherwise if people mixed usage of this, it would crash the repositories with confusing error messages.  Child repositories were already properly created with a terminating File.separator.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    New matcher: IsSingleRecipient
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Added spam blacklist checking for 3 spam blacklists that make this available in a simple DNS lookup check.  All free services through mail-abuse.org.  Added to default configuration in config.xml
  </action>
  <action dev="PU" type="code">
    Added first testing program.  This would recreate file stuck problem.  Would be good to build collection of testing utilities in this new package.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="docs">
    Documented what all the jars are in the lib directory (what they're called, where they're from)
  </action>
</release>

<release version="1.2" date="16-Oct-2000">
  <action dev="SK" type="design">
    Abstracted mailet API to be Avalon (implementation) independent
  </action>
  <action dev="CB" type="code">
    Abstracted mail repository in JAMES/Avalon to allow more varied implementations.
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Database implementations of mail repositories
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Changed remote delivery to use an outgoing spool with a specified number of delivery threads
  </action>
  <action dev="CB" type="code">
    Experimental implementation of LDAP user manager
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Reworked mailets and matchers to fit new API and added many more classes
  </action>
  <action dev="CBSK" type="update">
    Fixed some bugs in POP3 server
  </action>
  <action dev="CB" type="update">
    Added full TLS support in POP3 (POP3S)
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Fixed sorting of MX records so it attempts delivery in correct order
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="update">
    Changed remote manager to not allow a login if an admin account's password is empty,
    and sets the root account's password empty by default (so you have to set one... prevents someone
    from knowing the password to your system out of the box)
  </action>
</release>

<release version="1.1" date="27-Jul-2000">
  <action dev="??" type="code">
    Unknown changes
  </action>
  <action dev="SK" type="code">
    Made DNS functionality a separate block
  </action>
</release>

<release version="1.0" date="26-Feb-2000">
  <action dev="SKFB" type="code">
    Added DNS stuff to remote delivery.
  </action>
  <action dev="FB" type="code">
    Add some autodetect support for easier configuration.
  </action>
  <action dev="FB" type="code">
    Add support for Mailet.
  </action>
  <action dev="FB" type="update">
    Add Mailet interface draft.
  </action>
</release>

<release version="0.9.5" date="2000">
  <action dev="FB" type="update">
    Split the SMTP Server in a protocol handler and a MailServer available to
    all Avalon blocks.
  </action>
  <action dev="FB" type="update">
    Tune MessageContainer class.
  </action>
</release>

 <release version="0.9-dev" date="Can't remember">
  <action dev="FB" type="update">
    Based on much code from Serge Knystautas first implementation of JAMES on
    top of the Avalon framework.
  </action>
</release>

</changes>