<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Installation</title>
  <author email="sergek@lokitech.com">Serge Knystautas</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Step 0: Building. (only necessary for daily snapshots)">

  <p>
    If you have downloaded a regular distribution, you do not need to
    build James.  Proceed directory to Step 1.
  </p>

  <p>
    To compile James from sources you will need <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a>.
    This is a Java-tailored, XML-configured, extensible build or make system.
    We are currently using Ant 1.1, although documentation generation requires Ant 1.2.
  </p>

  <p>
    If you have downloaded a daily snapshot, you need to build a
    distribution.  James uses Ant (<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/</a>) to
    compile and package its distribution.  Once you have installed Ant,
    extracted the snapshot to your favorite folder, cd to that folder
    and run the "dist" task by calling "ant dist".  This will create the
    distribution in the "./dist" folder as well as create .tgz and .zip
    copies of this folder.  This "./dist" folder is the distribution
    folder used in Step 1 and beyond.  You may either cd to ./dist, or
    you may copy and rename the dist folder to your new favorite folder.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Step 1: Installation.">
  <p>
    Download distibution. Extract all files in your favorite folder.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Step 2: Configuration.">
  <p>
    Read the short and snappy documentation at docs/index.html for a proper
    overview of configuring the system.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Summary</b> (for impatient people)
  </p>
  <p>
    M$ users should just run /bin/run.bat. Unix users will find run.sh
    under the same folder. A JVM must be in the path.
    Running [run* -help] will provide a simple command line help.
  </p>
  <p>
    Most UNIX systems require superuser privileges to open sockets below 1024,
    which includes the IANA-standard SMTP (on port 25) and POP3 (on port 110).
    These default ports can be changed in the conf.xml file. (Obviously, you
    would then need to reconfigure your clients. This may not be an option if
    you want to receive mail from external mailservers.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The Avalon framework will unpack the neccessay configuration files and wait
    for you to configure them. For basic use, you only need to set two items
    in the JAMES.conf.xml file: a root password for the remote administration
    facility and the IP address of a DNS server. Once you have edited the
    configuration files, press 'Enter' on the terminal where Avalon is waiting.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Step 4: Kickstart.">
  <p>
    Once started you'll see a message saying Avalon is running. This means that
    Avalon has loaded JAMES and every other needed Block (see /logs/avalon.log)
    and is now waiting for a socket request.
    Since at the beginning James is empty, it will not have any local users
    registered.
    To register a local user open a telnet session with localhost on port 4555,
    log in as root ("root[enter]  &lt;password-you-set-in-conf.xml&gt;[enter]") and
    type "help" for a list of available commands in the "JAMES remote
    administrator tool". It is really a basic set but should allow you to test
    installation.
  </p>
  <p>
    Once you have some local users registered, try sending mail to one of them
    @localhost with SMTP (port 25) (assuming you have not changed the default
    server names in the conf.xml file). You'll see the mail appear under
    ../var/mail/localinbox/[user].
    Try now to retrieve that mail using POP3 (port 110).
    Trace out JAMES actions in /logs/*info.log.
    Action that will be taken by JAMES on incoming mail are configurated in
    the mailet pipe line (/conf/james.conf.xml). Look at it if you want to
    understand what's happening.
  </p>
  <p>
  Good luck :)
  </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
