<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>- Overview</title>
  <author email="sergek@lokitech.com">Serge Knystautas</author>
    <author email="danny@thought.co.uk">Danny Angus</author>
 </properties>

<body>
<section name="What is it?">
<p> The Java Apache Mail Enterprise Server (a.k.a. Apache James) is a 100% pure Java server, designed to be a complete and portable enterprise mail engine solution based on currently available open protocols (SMTP, POP3, NTTP). </p>
<p>James is also a mail application platform. <br/>The James project hosts the Apache Mailet API, and James provides and implementation of this mail application platform API.  </p>
<p>James is based upon the Apache Avalon application framework. (For more information about Avalon, please go to <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon">http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon</a>)</p>
<p>James requires Java 2 (specific requirement is the JRE 1.3, JRE 1.4 is not yet fully supported). </p>
<subsection name="news">
<p><b>We've added an FAQ page.</b><br/>There are only two FAQ's so far, but its a beginning (the link is on the left)</p>

<p><b>Version 2.0a2 is now available.</b></p>
<p>This new version contains a number of important bugfixes and performance improvements over v2.0a1</p>
<p><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-james/release/">Binary &amp; Source release of 2.0a2</a></p>
</subsection>
</section><section name="Design Objectives">
<p>These are some of the currently implemented features:</p>
<p><i><b>Complete portability</b></i>  Apache James is be a 100% pure Java application
       based on the Java 2 platform and the JavaMail 1.2 API.
  </p>
  <p><i><b>Protocol abstraction</b></i>  Unlike other mail engines, protocols are seen only
       like "communication languages" ruling comunications between clients and
       the server. Apache James is not be tied to any particular protocol but
       follow an abstracted server design (like JavaMail did on the
       client side)</p>
    <p><i><b>Complete solution</b></i>  the mail system is able to handle both mail
       transport and storage in a single server application. Apache James
       works alone without the need for any other server or solution.</p>
    <p><i><b>Mailet support</b></i>  Apache James supports the Apache Mailet API. A Mailet
       is a discrete piece of mail-processing logic which is incorporated into
       a Mailet-compliant mail-server's processing. This easy-to-write,
       easy-to-use pattern allows developers to build powerful customized mail
       systems. Examples of the services a Mailet might provide include: a
       mail-to-fax or mail-to-phone transformer, a filter, a language translator, a mailing
       list manager, etc. Several Mailets are included in the JAMES
       distribution (see <a href="configuration_v2_0.html">Configuration</a>).</p>
    <p><i><b>Resource abstraction</b></i>  Like protocols, resources are abstracted and,
       accessed through defined interfaces (JavaMail for transport, JDBC for
       spool storage or user accounts in RDBMS's, Apache Mailet API). The server is
       highly modular and reuse solutions from other projects.</p>
    <p><i><b>Secure and multi-threaded design</b></i>  Based on the technology developed
       for the Apache JServ servlet engine, Apache James has a careful,
       security-oriented, full multi-threaded design, to allow performance,
       scalability and mission-critical use.</p>
    <p>Anything else you may want if you help us write it :-)</p>
</section>
<section name="Feature Status">
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Item</th>
        <th>Status (v2.0a2)</th>
        <th>Since</th>
        <th>First released</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>SMTP server</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.0</td>
        <td>0.95</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Mailet Engine</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>0.95</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>FileSystem mailboxes/spool</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>RDBMS mailboxes/spool</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>POP3 server</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.1</td>
        <td>1.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>RDBMS - Users</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.2.1</td>
        <td>1.2.1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>LDAP Support - Users</td>
        <td>Experimental</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TLS Support - POP3</td>
        <td>Experimental</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Remote Manager</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.0</td>
        <td>1.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TLS Support - Remote Manager</td>
        <td>Stable</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>NNTP server</td>
        <td>Experimental</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
        <td>1.2</td>
      </tr>
    </table>

</section>

</body>
</document>
