<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>TODO</title>
  <author email="sergek@lokitech.com">Serge Knystautas</author>
  <author email="charles@benett1.co.uk">Charles Benett</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="TODO">
<p>This is a living document that will give new and existing volunteers some areas where we need help.  As always, any help is appreciated, be it documentation, code, suggestions, or feedback.
Last Updated  20 April 2002.</p>
</section>

<section name="High Priority">
<p>Refactor to use the latest Avalon releases.</p>
<p>Determine a way to support multiple domains.</p>
<p>Update and write more documentation, including  a) how to setup user accounts for pop3 delivery/retrieval, b) how to setup a database for message storage, c) how to setup a database for user accounts, d) how to write a mailet, e) how to setup and use SMTP auth to allow remote delivery for valid users.</p>
<p>Improve the debugging output, including a) catching that DNS servers are not correct (at least have DNS log channel record DNS server usage)</p>
<p>Make log files appending and at 'INFO' level (not debug) by default</p>
<p>Get IMAP server to alpha standard, ie basic interoperation with e-mail clients.</p>
</section>

<section name="Medium Priority">
<p>Get classloaders working so custom mailets don't have to be in james.jar (SK: I suggest adding support for apps/james/classes and apps/james/lib directories and have the MailetLoader and MatcherLoader use these in addition to system level classpath).</p>
<p>Refactor RemoteManager to be an object that can be controlled via RMI or what have you, and have the remote manager telnet interface make appropriate calls to this interface.</p>
<p>Add support in the RemoteManager to manage repositories.  This includes listing what's in a repository, viewing individual messages, deleting messages, copying messages, and moving messages.</p>
<p>Implement an imap:// repository implementation.  The goal would be to allow you to transfer messages using the RemoteManager from an IMAP account from or to a James message repository.</p>
<p>Write an ezmlm comparable listserv manager</p>
<p>Add regex matchers</p>
<p>Add support in the CharTerminatedInputStream to support read(byte[]) instead of just read().</p>
<p>Fix NNTP authentication</p>
<p>Fix NNTP ssl</p>
<p>Write more documentation. </p>
<p>Add #news namespace to IMAP system</p>
<p>Revisit UserRepository - after doing IMAP List &amp; Subscribe</p>
<p>Add needed functions to RemoteManager, Including Stop and ReConfigure (?), Reinject mail (this should just be copying/moving messages...), Store RemoteManger password securely.</p>
<p>Add support for better mailet router/processing (maybe like RequestDispatcher) - Use Stage/Pipline pattern</p>
<p>Add support for deployable message processing apps using Camelot pattern</p>
<p>Give admins option to enforce one access at a time to a POP3 mailbox.</p>
<p>Tie in the NNTP Repository with POP/SMTP/IMAP repository structure.</p>
<p>Test and move RMI interface from proposal directory to main branch.</p>
</section>

<section name="Low Priority">
<p>Add support for DRAC login/relay allowing</p>
<p>Enable read receipts to be handled properly (?)</p>
<p>Add support for mbox mail repository format.</p>
<p>Add support for mail.dir (?) repository format.</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

