<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>TODO</title>
  <author email="sergek@lokitech.com">Serge Knystautas</author>
  <author email="charles@benett1.co.uk">Charles Benett</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="TODO">
<p>This is a living document that will give new and existing volunteers some areas where we need help.  As always, any help is appreciated, be it documentation, code, suggestions, or feedback.
Last Updated  30 October 2001.</p>
</section>

<section name="High Priority">
<p>Get classloaders working so custom mailets don't have to be in james.bar</p>
<p>Update and write more documentation, including  a) how to setup user accounts for pop3 delivery/retrieval, b) how to setup a database for message storage, c) how to setup a database for user accounts, d) how to write a mailet.</p>
<p>Make JamesSpoolManager disposable, calling destroy on mailets, for a graceful shutdown.</p>
<p>Add regex matchers</p>
</section>

<section name="Medium Priority">
<p>Determine a way to support multiple domains</p>
<p>Fix NNTP authentication</p>
<p>Fix NNTP ssl</p>
<p>Write more documentation. </p>
<p>Write more documentation. </p>
<p>Get IMAP server to alpha standard, ie basic interoperation with e-mail clients.</p>
<p>Add #news namespace to IMAP system</p>
<p>Revisit UserRepository - after doing IMAP List &amp; Subscribe</p>
<p>Add needed functions to RemoteManager, Including Stop and ReConfigure, Reinject mail, Store RemoteManger password securely.</p>
<p>Add support for better mailet router/processing (maybe like RequestDispatcher) - Use Stage/Pipline pattern</p>
<p>Add support for deployable message processing apps using Camelot pattern</p>
<p>Give admins option to enforce one access at a time to a POP3 mailbox.</p>
<p>Tie in the NNTP Repository with POP/SMTP/IMAP repository structure.</p>
<p>Test and move RMI interface from proposal directory to main branch.</p>
</section>

<section name="Low Priority">

<p>Add support for DRAC login/relay allowing</p>
<p>Enable read receipts to be handled properly</p>
<p>Add support for mbox mail repository format.</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

