<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>TODO</title>
  <author email="sergek@lokitech.com">Serge Knystautas</author>
  <author email="charles@benett1.co.uk">Charles Benett</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="TODO">
<p>This is a living document that will give new and existing volunteers some areas where we need help.  As always, any help is appreciated, be it documentation, code, suggestions, or feedback.
Last Updated 17 May 2001.</p>
</section>
<section name="High Priority">
<p>Port existing documentation to xdocs format</p>
<p>Bundle docs in dist</p>
<p>Allow RemoteManager to change passwords of users (change attribute)<b> In proposals dir </b> </p>
<p>Revive RDBMS support for messages and users. Possibly move from town to straight jdbc, or jakarta-turbine.</p>

</section>

<section name="Medium Priority">
<p>Enable multiple domains/ virtual hosting</p>
<p>Rewrite SMTP and POP3 handlers to use streams not MimeMessage objects</p>
<p>Let RemoteDelivery send all messages to a single remote server (acting like a gateway, relay or 'smart' host) </p>
<p>Improve exception management in RemoteDelivery mailet and general notices of why delivery failures occur.</p>
<p>Add support for regex inside most matchers and thereby consolidate a few of them.</p>
<p>Write more documentation. </p>
<p>Make James stoppable (elegantly)</p>
<p>Get IMAP server to alpha standard, ie basic interoperation with e-mail clients.</p>
<p>Add #news namespace to IMAP system</p>
<p>Revisit UserRepository - after doing IMAP List &amp; Subscribe</p>
<p>Make James reconfigurable/contextualizable/composable.</p>
<p>Reinject error/spam mails incorrecty handled.</p>
<p>Add needed functions to RemoteManager, Including Stop and ReConfigure, Reinject mail, Store RemoteManger password securely.</p>
<p>Add support for better mailet router/processing (maybe like RequestDispatcher) - Use Stage/Pipline pattern</p>
<p>Add support for deployable message processing apps using Camelot pattern</p>
<p>Give admins option to enforce one access at a time to a POP3 mailbox.</p>
<p>Simplify email aliasing</p>
<p>Tie in the NNTP Repository with POP/SMTP/IMAP repository structure.</p>
</section>

<section name="Low Priority">

<p>Add support for DRAC login/relay allowing</p>
<p>Review threadpooling - is it dynamic?</p>
<p>Enable read receipts to be handled properly</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

