<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

  <properties>
     <title>James 3 - Index</title>
  </properties>

<body>

  <section name="James 3.0-M1">
  
	    <p>The Java Apache Mail Enterprise Server (a.k.a. Apache James) is a 100% pure Java SMTP, IMAP4 and POP3 Mail 
	      server designed to be a complete and portable enterprise mail engine solution.  
	      James is based on currently available open protocols.</p>
	    
	    <p>This documentation is intended to be an introduction to the concepts behind the James usage, as well 
	      as a guide to <a href="installation_instructions.html">install</a>, <a href="configuration_instructions.html">configure</a> 
	      and <a href="build_james.html">develop</a> James server.</p>
	    
	    <p>You can download stables releases from <a href="http://james.apache.org/download.cgi">here</a>
	      (or latest snapshots from <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/james/nightly/">here</a>).</p>
	
        <table>
        
         <tr><td width="50%">

          <subsection name="Configureable">
          
            <p>Configure the stores,... via the well-known Spring framework - <a href="configuration.html">read more</a>.</p>
        
            <img src="images/conf/config_example.png" height="400px" />
        
          </subsection>
          
         </td><td width="50%">

          <subsection name="Manageable">
        
            <p>Manage domains, users,... via well-known JMX tools - <a href="management.html">read more</a>.</p>
            
            <img src="images/jmx_management/jmx_user_part.png" />

          </subsection>
          
         </td></tr>
        
          <tr><td width="50%">

          <subsection name="Performant">
           
            <p>A special focuss has been brought to the performance: James can process more than
               100 mails per second - <a href="feature_performance.html">read more</a></p>
        
            <img src="images/jmx_monitoring/jmx_process_root.png" height="400px" />
        
          </subsection>
         
         </td><td width="50%">

          <subsection name="Secured">
        
            <p>James is a secured mail server by default - <a href="feature_security.html">read more</a>.</p>
        
          </subsection>
          
         </td></tr>
        
         <tr><td width="50%">
        
  	      <subsection name="Extensible">
	    
	        <p>James serves as a mail application platform.  The James project hosts the Apache Mailet API, 
	          and provides the Mailet container.  These features makes it easy to design, write, and deploy 
	          custom applications for mail processing.  This modularity and ease of customization is one of James' 
	          strengths, and can allow administrators to produce powerful applications surprisingly easily.</p>
	 
	        <p>James 3.0 is now built on top of Spring 3.0 in replacement of trunk version of the <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/">Avalon</a> Application Framework.
	           With Spring, We keep the good development practices introduced by Avalon such as 
	           Component Oriented Programming and  Inversion of Control. 
	           The stable and robust Spring container provides a strong foundation for the James server.</p>
	    
	        <p>The internal and exposed APIs for this 3.0-M1 release are under current validation and are 
	          expected to be subject to change - <a href="dev_architecture.html">read more</a>.</p>
	         
            <img src="images/uml/org.apache.james_package_part.png" width="400px" />
        
  	      </subsection>
  	      
  	    </td><td width="50%">
	
	      <subsection name="Features">
	    
	        <p>James 3.0 represents the leading edge of development. This codestream has many more
	          features than the 2.x code, but is not as well tested in production. Reasonable
	          configuration compatibility has been retained with 3.0. James 3.0 requires Java 1.5 but Java 1.6 is recommended. 
	          A migration guide for users willing to upgrade from 2.3 to 3.0 is <a href="james_upgrade.html">available</a>. 
	          The NNTP News server present in James 2.3 has been removed from the 3.0 release line.</p>
	    
	        <ul>
	          <li>100% pure Java Mail server designed to be a complete and portable enterprise 
	              mail engine solution.</li>
	          <li>Supports currently available IETF protocols, including SMTP, LMTP, POP3 and IMAP4 
	              James is able to store user and message data either in a file-system (Maildir), any JPA-compatible database
	              and even JCR, allowing fast, reliable, even real-time replicated storage.</li>
	          <li>Provides a powerful, flexible mail application engine through support for the Apache Mailet 
	              API.  With its Mailet pipeline architecture, James can be used not only to provide standard e-mail 
	              services, but also to implement custom e-mail applications.</li>
	          <li>Deployed in production environments and has proven itself to be a robust 
	              and high performance mail solution.  Tests indicate that version 3.0 
	              is able to maintain a constant mail throughput rate of thousands of 
	              messages/minute for continuous periods.</li>
  	        </ul>
	      
  	      </subsection>
  	      
  	    </td></tr>
  	      
   	    </table>

  </section>

</body>

</document>
